A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Elinor Barber FA632
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Elinor Barber
1967-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA632
5.72 Cubic Feet
The papers of Elinor Barber, Program Officer of the Office of the Vice President, International Division (OVP/ID) from 1967 to 1981, document her activities and those of the International Division, particularly those related to Foundation programs on the rights and status of women, affirmative action, and education, during this period. They were sent to the Foundation's Archives in January 1982. The papers consist primarily of correspondence, memoranda, and Barber's rough notes summarizing meetings and conferences she attended. They are divided into two series. Arrangement of the series and of files within the series is based as closely as possible on the original order in which the papers were maintained.
Biographical / Historical
Elinor G. Barber, Program Officer of the Ford Foundation's Office of the Vice President, International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from October 1967 until her departure in October 1981. During this period, she held the following positions:
• October 1967, Program Officer, Office of Planning and Evaluation, International Division
• October 1969, Program Officer, Office of the Vice President, International Division
Ms. Barber also served as a consultant to the Foundation's U.S. and International Affairs Program between November 15, 1981 and February 1, 1982.
Elinor Barber was born on November 11, 1924. She received her B.A. in History from Vassar College in 1945 and was elected Phi Beta Kappa. She earned the M.A. and Ph.D. degrees in History from Radcliffe College in 1946 and 1951, respectively.
Prior to Barber's career with the Ford Foundation, she held the following positions:
• 1949 - 52, Instructor, Smith College
• 1956 - 57, 1967, Lecturer, Columbia University
• 1961- 67, Editor for Biographies, International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, Crowell, Collier and Macmillan
After her departure from the Foundation, she joined the Institute of International Education as Coordinator for Research.
Scope and Contents
Elinor Barber's papers document her Foundation activities from 1967 to 1981, particularly in the following areas:
• the activities of the International Division: the Office of the Vice President and the overseas field offices
• the activities of Ford Foundation committees, conferences, offices, and working groups on programs related to the rights and status of women; and on the Ford Foundation's internal and external affirmative action initiatives
• Ford Foundation studies or programs related to education, including the Barber/Ilchman International Studies Review for the Social Science Research Council; Foundation support of Language Education, particularly at the Center for Applied Linguistics (CAL); Barber's papers on Sex Differences in Education and on Rural Education; and Barber's contributions to the Education section of the March 1981 Information Paper presented to the Foundation's Board of Trustees.
The papers contain materials on policy planning, administration and evaluation, and meetings and conferences for the following programs in the International Division in effect at that time: Office of the Vice President (OVP), Asia and the Pacific (A&P), Europe and International Affairs (EIA), Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC), and Middle East and Africa (MEA).
There is correspondence for the years 1971 - 1981 between New York-based staff and overseas field staff of the International Division on the International Division's grant-making activities, particularly those related to the rights and status of women, and on Barber's trips to the field. There is also correspondence for the years 1973 - 1981 between Barber and Ford Foundation consultants, selected grantee and membership organizations, individuals and organizations seeking grants, and other donor organizations. Correspondents of special interest include Mary Jean Bowman, Arvonne Fraser, Adrienne Germain, Janet Giele, Hanna Papanek, and Audrey Smock.
There is extensive material on the activities of seven successive Foundation committees on programs for women's rights and for affirmative action for the years 1970 to 1981: the Committee on the Role of Women; the Task Force on the Status of Women; the Affirmative Action Committee; the Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs; the Committee on Women in International Programs; the Women's Programs Group; and the International Division Committee on Women. There is also material on the World Conference of the United Nations' International Women's Year in Mexico, 1975; on the NGO (Non-Governmental Organizations) Forum for the World Conference of the UN Decade for Women in Copenhagen, 1980; and on the Ford Foundation International Division's Conference on Women 's Programs, March 1980. The papers contain lists of participants, agenda, notes for discussion, and Barber's notes or memoranda summarizing the proceedings.
The papers contain materials related to programs for women's rights and status for the years 1970 - 1981 which were generated by Foundation offices and working groups in addition to those of the International Division, including the Higher Education and Research (HE&R), National Affairs (NA) and Population (POP) Offices, the Chafkin Working Group on Nutrition, and the Women's Program Group Task Force on the Military in Society. There are files of correspondence, interoffice memoranda, and Barber's rough notes concerning program planning, administration and evaluation; grant proposals and staff comment; and meetings she attended. Topics of special interest include: proposed programs on Training for Women Leaders at U.S. Universities (1977 - 1981); and discussions of the Percy Amendment (May 1974).
The papers are rich in material on the Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review (1979), a report conducted on behalf of the Social Sciences Research Council (SSRC) by Barber and Warren Ilchman which surveyed International Studies programs at thirteen U.S. universities. There are files of correspondence, memoranda, and notes on preliminary planning, questionnaire forms, scheduling, on-site contacts, responses from interviewees, coding format for data processing, preliminary conclusions, responses from recipients of the Review, and projected "next steps" for Foundation program planning.
The papers also contain a great deal of material on Foundation programs supporting Language Education for the years 1967 - 1980, particularly at the Center for Applied Linguistics (CAL). There are files of correspondence, memoranda, and notes on language teaching, research (especially in sociolinguistics and bilingual-bicultural education), and meetings and conferences attended.
Finally, there is material related to Barber's papers on the Role of Sex Differences in Educational Attainment (May 1977, July 1979); on Rural Education (Oct. 1979, Dec. 1979), including a presentation for the International Division Education Conference (Oct. 1979); and on the Education section of the March 1981 Information Paper presented to the Foundation's Board of Trustees. There are files of background material, rough drafts and staff comment, and responses from recipients.
Arrangement
The papers of Elinor Barber are divided into two series:
I. Correspondence Files
II. Subject Files
Separated Materials
Some groups of papers have been removed and placed with the appropriate record groups in the Ford Foundation Archives:
• Ford Foundation Conference Papers
• Minutes and Dockets of Trustee Meetings
• Staff and consultant reports and publications.
Their locations have been noted on cross-reference sheets. A list of titles of reports removed from the papers is appended to this register.
Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence Files, 1971 - 1981; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence Files (1971 - 1981), is the most extensive. It contains Barber's files of incoming and outgoing correspondence and inter-office memoranda.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into the following two sub-series:
  A. Alphabetical Files (4 boxes)
  B. International Division Files (3 boxes)
  - Alphabetical Files, A
    These files consist of Barber's selected incoming and outgoing correspondence with Ford Foundation colleagues and consultants, grantee and membership organizations, individuals and organizations seeking grants, and other donor organizations.
    These files are arranged alphabetically. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Abou-Saif, Layla, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abu-Nasr, Julinda (Institute for Women's Studies in Arab World - Beirut), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Agricultural Development Council, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aguiar, Neuma (IUPERJ grant), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AID (Arvonne Fraser), 1975 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Almy, Susan (Rockefeller Foundation), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Beardsley/Eddy/Richards Proposal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Boston Group Proposal, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bowman, Mary Jean, 1976 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bunting Institute (Radcliffe- Marion Kilson/Marina Horner), 1979 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bruce, Judith (Family Planning International Assistance), 1977 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bryn Mawr (April 10, 1976) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Burn, Barbara (President's Commission on Foreign Languages), 1978 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cassell, Joan, 1976 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - CEFRES (Francoise Latour), 1977 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chen, Marty (Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cole, Jonathan, 1974 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cole, Michael, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Columbia University (Jonathan Cole), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dandekar, Hemalata, 1979 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Elmendorf, Mary, 1973 - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Epstein/Senaratne Proposal, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Feminist Networking Proposals, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Film Proposals, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gephart - Gender and Society, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1980 - 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Germain, Adrienne, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Germain, Adrienne (International Women's Year Activities), 1974 - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Giele/Smock (International Project on the Status of Women), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Giele/Smock (International Project on the Status of Women), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Giele/Smock (International Project on the Status of Women), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Harris, Rosalind, 1977 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Human Rights/Women's Rights Proposals, 1975 - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Huntington, Suellen, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - International Center for Research on Women (Turbitt, Youseff/Buvinic), 1978 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - ISIS International (Judy Sidden), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Jamaican Women's Bureau, 1976 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Lazarus, Barbara, 1979 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Lee, Dr. Tai-Young (Korea Legal Aid Center), 1975 - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Leslie, Joanne, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Lipman-Blumen, Jean, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Luria, Zella, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Minge-Klevana, Wanda, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Minnesota, University of, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Money, John, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - National Council of Negro Women, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Overseas Development Council, 1976 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Overseas Education Fund, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Palmer, Ingrid (ILO), 1976 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Papanek, Hanna, 1974 - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Patton, Dorothy, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Porter, Leslie, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Rappoports/Safilios-Rothschild Proposal, 1976 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Safilios-Rothschild, Constantina, 1974 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Smock, Audrey, 1979 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Smock, Audrey, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Smock, Audrey, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Sostek, Anita M., 1979 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Tinker, Irene, 1979 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Treistman, Judith, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Turnabout (Roxanne Russell), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Wainerman, Catalina, 1977 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Wald, Patricia, 1974 - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - WEAL Fund, 1967 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Wellesley Center, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Whiting, Beatrice (Harvard University), 1975 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Women's World Banking, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - World Bank (Susan Cochrane), 1979 - I980 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Worldwatch, 1976 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Zeidenstein/Abdullah Proposal, 1975 - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - International Division Files, B
    These files consist of Barber's incoming and outgoing correspondence and inter-office memoranda within the Foundation's Office of the Vice President, International Division (OVP/ID), and with the ID field offices.
    These files are divided into the following programs of the International Division in effect at that time:
    • Asia and Pacific (A&P)
    • Europe and International Affairs (EIA)
    • Latin America (LAC)
    • Middle East and Africa (MEA)
    Each of these programs is further divided into the following sections:
    • Regional and Overseas Office Activities
    • Women-Related Activities
    • Field Trips
    The files in each section are arranged alphabetically by country. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - A&P Regional and Overseas Activities, 1972 - 1981 (Box 4, Frame 75)
    - Women-Related Activities (Bangladesh), 1972 - 1980 (Box 4, Frame 76)
    - Women-Related Activities (India), 1979 - 1981 (Box 4, Frame 77)
    - Women-Related Activities (India), 1972 - 1978 (Box 4, Frame 78)
    - Women-Related Activities (Pakistan), 1975 - 1976 (Box 4, Frame 79)
    - Women-Related Activities (Pakistan), 1972 - 1974 (Box 4, Frame 80)
    - Women-Related Activities (Philippines), 1974 - 1978 (Box 4, Frame 81)
    - Women-Related Activities (Thailand), 1972 - 1981 (Box 4, Frame 82)
    - Asia Trip, March 1981 (India and Indonesia), 1978 - 1981 (Box 5, Frame 83)
    - Asia Trip, January 1978 (Indonesia), 1977 - 1978 (Box 5, Frame 84)
    - Asia Trip, January 1978 (India), 1977 - 1978 (Box 5, Frame 85)
    - Asia Trip, January 1978 (Philippines), 1977 - 1978 (Box 5, Frame 86)
    - Asia Trip, January 1978 (Thailand), 1976 - 1978 (Box 5, Frame 87)
    - Asia Trip, March 1975, 1974 - 1975 (Box 5, Frame 88)
    - Japan Trip, August 1972 (Box 5, Frame 89)
    - EIA Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1980 - 1981 (Box 5, Frame 90)
    - EIA Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1977 - 1979 (Box 5, Frame 91)
    - EIA Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1971 - 1976 (Box 5, Frame 92)
    - EGB Trip to England, March 1980, 1979 - 1980 (Box 5, Frame 93)
    - EGB Trip to England and Wales, Sept. 1978 (Box 5, Frame 94)
    - EGB Trip to Europe, Sept. 1976, 1976 - 1977 (Box 5, Frame 95)
    - LAC Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1975 - 1980 (Box 5, Frame 96)
    - LAC Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1972 - 1974 (Box 5, Frame 97)
    - Women-Related Activities (Brazil), 1980 - 1981 (Box 5, Frame 98)
    - Women-Related Activities (Brazil), 1979 (Box 5, Frame 99)
    - Women-Related Activities (Brazil), 1973 - 1978 (Box 5, Frame 100)
    - Women-Related Activities (Colombia), 1973 - 1981 (Box 6, Frame 101)
    - Women-Related Activities (Mexico), 1973 - 1980 (Box 6, Frame 102)
    - Women's Program Review, Mexico - Background Correspondence (May 1979), 1976 - 1979 (Box 6, Frame 103)
    - Brazil Trip, February 1980, 1976 - 1980 (Box 6, Frame 104)
    - Latin America Trip June 1979, 1976 - 1979 (Box 6, Frame 105)
    - South America Trip June 1975, 1974 - 1975 (Box 6, Frame 106)
    - MEA Regional and Overseas Office Activities, 1972 - 1977 (Box 6, Frame 107)
    - East and Southern Africa Office Activities, 1977 - 1981 (Box 6, Frame 108)
    - East and Southern Africa Office Activities, 1972 - 1976 (Box 6, Frame 109)
    - North Africa Office Activities, 1972 - 1973 (Box 6, Frame 110)
    - West Africa Office Activities, 1978 - 1981 (Box 6, Frame 111)
    - West Africa Office Activities, 1976 - 1977 (Box 6, Frame 112)
    - West Africa Office Activities, 1972 - 1975 (Box 6, Frame 113)
    - Women-Related Activities (Middle East), 1972 - 1980 (Box 6, Frame 114)
    - Africa Trip, Oct./Nov. 1976 (Box 6, Frame 115)
    - Africa Trip - Language, Oct./Nov. 1976 (Box 6, Frame 116)
    - East Africa Trip March 1980 (Box 6, Frame 117)
    - West Africa Trip February 1980, 1978 - 1980 (Box 6, Frame 118)
- Subject Files, 1967 - 1981; II
  Series II, Subject Files (1967 - 1981), contains informational files arranged by subject. This series is divided into the following two sub-series:
  A. Affirmative Action/Women (3 boxes)
  B. Education (3 boxes)
  - Affirmative Action/Women, A
    These files consist of material on the activities of Ford Foundation committees and conferences, offices and selected working groups on the Foundation's affirmative action initiatives, and on Foundation programs related to women's rights and status.
    These files are divided into the following two sections:
    • Committees/Conferences
    • Office/Working Groups
    Within each section, the folders are arranged alphabetically. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Committee on Women in International Programs, 1979 (Box 7, Frame 119)
    - Committee on Women in International Programs, 1978 (Box 7, Frame 120)
    - Committee on Women in International Programs, 1977 (Box 7, Frame 121)
    - Committee on Women in International Programs, 1976 (Box 7, Frame 122)
    - Committee on Women in International Programs, 1974 - 1975 (Box 7, Frame 123)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1977 - 1978 (Box 7, Frame 124)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1976 May - December (Box 7, Frame 125)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1976 January - March (Box 7, Frame 126)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1975 (Box 7, Frame 127)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1974 September - December (Box 8, Frame 128)
    - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1974 January - August (Box 8, Frame 129)
    - Expanded Program Activities Concerning Women, 1980 (Box 8, Frame 130)
    - FF Programs for Women - Budgets for FY 1980 - 1981, 1979 - 1980 (Box 8, Frame 131)
    - Information Paper on Programs for Women, 1979 (Box 8, Frame 132)
    - Internal Affirmative Action, 1974 - 1981 (Box 8, Frame 133)
    - Internal Affirmative Action, 1971 - 1973 (Box 8, Frame 134)
    - ID Committee on Women (1980), 1980 - 1981 (Box 8, Frame 135)
    - ID Conference on Women's Programs (March 1980) (Box 8, Frame 136)
    - Programs Related to Women, 1970 - 1971 (Box 8, Frame 137)
    - Task Force on Status of Women, 1973 July - December (Box 8, Frame 138)
    - Task Force on Status of Women, 1973 January - June (Box 8, Frame 139)
    - Task Force on Status of Women, 1972 September - December (Box 9, Frame 140)
    - Task Force on Status of Women, 1972 January - August (Box 9, Frame 141)
    - U.N. International Women's Year - NGO Forum, Mid - Decade, Copenhagen, 1980 (Box 9, Frame 142)
    - U.N. International Women's Year - World Conference Mexico, 1975, 1974 - 1976 (Box 9, Frame 143)
    - Women's Programs DAP - 769-0804, 1975 - 1980 (Box 9, Frame 144)
    - Women's Program Group, 1981 (Box 9, Frame 145)
    - Women's Program Group, 1980 April - December (Box 9, Frame 146)
    - Women's Program Group, 1980 January - March (Box 9, Frame 147)
    - Chafkin Working Group on Nutrition, 1979 - 1981 (Box 9, Frame 148)
    - Child Care/Development/Socialization, 1977 - 1980 (Box 9, Frame 149)
    - National Affairs Office Activities, 1972 - 1975 (Box 9, Frame 150)
    - Percy Amendment, 1974 - 1975 (Box 10, Frame 151)
    - Population Office Activities, 1975 - 1979 (Box 10, Frame 152)
    - Population Office Activities, 1973 - 1974 (Box 10, Frame 153)
    - Training for Women Leaders at U.S. Universities, 1977 - 1981 (Box 10, Frame 154)
    - Women and the Military, 1981 June - September (Box 10, Frame 155)
    - Women and the Military, 1981 January - May (Box 10, Frame 156)
    - Women and the Military, 1980 (Box 10, Frame 157)
    - Women in Agricultural Development, 1974 - 1980 (Box 10, Frame 158)
    - Women Migrants and Refugees, 1980 (Box 10, Frame 159)
    - Women - Miscellaneous, 1974 - 1979 (Box 10, Frame 160)
  - Education, B
    These files consist of material on Ford Foundation programs or studies related to education.
    These files are divided into the following six sections:
    • Barber/Ilchman Social Science Research Council Review of International Studies
    • Language Education
    • Sex Differences in Education
    • Rural Education
    • Higher Education and Research (HER) Office Activities
    • March 1981 Information Paper - Education
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review, 1979 (Box 10, Frame 161)
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review, 1978 (Box 10, Frame 162)
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review - Background Material, 1979 (Box 10, Frame 163)
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review - Responses, 1980 (Box 10, Frame 164)
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review - Responses, 1979 July - December (Box 10, Frame 165)
    - Barber/Ilchman SSRC Review - Responses, 1979 May - June (Box 10, Frame 166)
    - Columbia University (Feb. 1-2, 1979) (Box 11, Frame 167)
    - Cornell University (Jan. 29-30, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 168)
    - University of Chicago (Feb. 8-9, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 169)
    - University of Michigan (Feb. 27-28, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 170)
    - Michigan State University (Feb. 19-21, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 171)
    - Stanford University (Feb. 15-16, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 172)
    - University of Texas (Feb. 26-27, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 173)
    - Tulane University (Mar. 1-2, 1979) (Box 11, Folder 174)
    - University of California at Berkeley, 1975 - 1979 (Box 12, Folder 175)
    - University of California at Berkeley (Feb. 22-23, 1979) (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - University of Washington (Feb. 12-13, 1979) (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - University of Wisconsin (Feb. 15-16, 1979) (Box 12, Folder 178)
    - Yale University (Jan. 29-30, 1979) (Box 12, Folder 179)